A Guide to the National Committee on United States-China Relations records, RG 9, Accession 9 FA1191
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Board of Directors, Committees, and Members records, 1965-2012; 11; 3.04 Cubic Feet 8 containers
  - Program Expansion Proposal, 1967 June 9 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Program Summary and Proposals, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Original typescript, prepared for Board of Directors meeting, March 18, 1968. Folder labeled "First Edition."
  - Program Summary, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    "Original," 38 pages, plus Appendices A - D, 28 pages. Report covers period March 1967 - April/May 1968. File also includes earlier and slightly variant copy of the report, inscribed "Mang."
  - Program Summary, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Program Summaries and Brochures, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Includes first annual program summary, May 1967; Six Month Summary, May - October 1967; communications and symposia proposals, March - June 1968; summary of activities, October 1969; brochure for China Trade Briefing, April 20. 1970.
  - National Committee Brochure, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Small brochure mock-ups, pricing, and distribution.
  - Stationery, Reprints, and Printed Material, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Layout originals. Archival copies have been substituted for the originals in cases where the glued copies are disintegrating.
  - Speaker Requests and Conferences Aids Program, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    NCUSCR consultatation service provided speaker referrals or literature for groups planning programs on China.
  - Conferences Aids Program, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - International Economic Council, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    National Committee speakers for proposed IEC meeting on China. IEC contribution refunded when meeting arrangements fell through.
  - Seminar Program Summary (Meetings and Participants), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    Program summary for 1967-1968.
  - Seminar Records and Summaries, 1967-1970 (Box 3, Folder 32-33)
    Material removed from ring binder. Lists of seminar programs and attendees for: Foundation Executives, Community Leaders; Senatorial Assistants, Young Business Executives, Congressmen, Aerospace Executives, California Aerospace Executives, Trade Study, Washington Journalists, Regional Journalists, New York Journalists, Ad Hoc Meetings in New York, Special Meetings in Washington, and Washington Organizational Leaders. Only one meeting for 1970.
  - Articles of Incorporation, Bylaws, Meeting Minutes, 1966 - 1968 March (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Volume includes revised version of NCUSCR Bylaws, (August 28, 1967); Meeting Minutes (Development Committee, Board of Directors, Executive Committee, General Membership), 1966 - 1968 February 2.
  - Bylaws (and Amendments), 1966 November 4 - 1967 August 28 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    NCUSCR Bylaws as amended November 4, 1966 (2 copies), plus individual amendments from September 9, 1966 through August 28, 1967.
  - Bylaws, 1967 June 9 - 1983 October 31 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    NCUSCR Bylaws as amended June 9, 1967; October 29, 1975 - July 14, 1981; October 31, 1983.
  - Bylaws, 1990 March 13 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    NCUSCR Bylaws as amended March 13, 1990, with corrections and proposed changes. Includes correspondence, August - October 1990, concerning possible changes. Some of the marginal comments may stem from a later review of the bylaws.
  - Bylaws, 2006 November 9-10 - 2012 January 20 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    NCUSCR Bylaws as amended November 9-10, 2006; April 7, 2009; and January 20, 2012. The 2009 bylaws include some marginal notes and corrections
  - Membership and Invitation Lists, 1978-1982 (Box 4, Folder 39-41)
    Includes membership list by region, 1978; lists of musicians and performing artists, circa 1979?; master list, annual members meeting, October 22, 1980; invitation list, January 29, 1982; alphabetical membership lists, 1979 - 1981.
  - Old Membership Lists, 1981-1985 (Box 4, Folder 42-43)
    Includes membership list by state (1982).
  - Membership List Corrections, 1978; 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    Includes names to be removed from membership lists, 1978.
  - Contributions - Acknowledgment Letters, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 45-47)
  - Contributions - Acknowledgment Letters, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 48-49)
  - Contributions - Acknowledgment Letters, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Contributions - Acknowledgment Letters, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Contributions - Acknowledgment Letters, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 52-53)
  - Contributions - Acknowledgment Letters, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Barber Conable - House Ways and Means Committee Testimony, 1994 February 24 (Box 46, Folder 443)
    Testimony on U. S. - China Relations to the Submcommittee on Trade.
  - Praises, Compliments, Just How Great We Really Are, 1988-2001 (Box 46, Folder 444)
  - NCUSCR Holiday Cards, Undated (Box 46, Folder 445)
    Printed greeting cards from National Committee Staff, late 1960s-1970s.
  - Presidential Search Committee, 1997-1998 (Box 51, Folder 492)
    John L. Holden was selected to replace Douglas P. Murray as president of the NCUSCR, effective September 1, 1998.
  - Search Committee and Election for Chairperson, 2000-2001 (Box 51, Folder 493)
    Carla A. Hills was elected as new chair of the National Committee in March 2001, replacing Barber Conable.
  - National Committee Prospectus and Program Summary, 1967 May (Box 51, Folder 494)
    Origins, Organizational Structure, Program summary and Prospectus, Financial Summary, and Appendices.
  - National Committee History - General, 1977-1999 (Box 51, Folder 495)
    File contains sections from Robert and Pamela Mang's History of the Origins of the NCUSCR (mainly the appendices); Proposals to China for 1979 exchange programs; Recognition of the National Committee at Concert celebrating the centennial of Zhou En Lai's birth, February 28, 1998.
  - National Committee History - Beijing Center (Background and Planning), 1988-1997 (Box 51, Folder 496)
  - NCUSCR Press Releases, 1973-1998 (Box 51, Folder 497)
  - Early Organization and Program Information, 1967 (Box 61, Folder 598)
    File consists of Appendices A-E, which may have formed part of a fundraising proposal. Includes list of NCUSCR members (as of July 14, 1967); Program of conference at Berkeley, December 1964; syllabi for lecture programs and seminar in Boston; NCUSCR statement of purpose, organizing group, and tentative program, plus letter of invitation, April 14, 1966.
  - Members Files (General), 1978-2007 (Box 61, Folder 599)
    Correspondence and clippings pertaining to various members. Includes William J. Cunningham, Elizabeth Knup, Maurice B. Levien, Robert Nederlander Jr., Rodney W. Nichols, Dwight Perkins (1969), David Rockefeller Jr., Robert A. Scalapino (2007), David Shambaugh, Seymour Topping, Elizabeth Wishnick.
  - National Committee Brochures and Publications, 1965-1970 (Box 61, Folder 600)
    File of brochures on programs, membership, and topical subjects. Includes brochure from National Conference on the United States and China, 1965 April 29-30; Seminar programs, 1967; Harald Munthe-Kaas, 1968; etc.
- NCUSCR Presidents' Files, 1974-2002; 14; 4.18 Cubic Feet 11 letter document boxes
  Series 14, Presidents Files, in RG 9 contains the chronological correspondence files (plus some general correspondence and speech files) of Arthur H. Rosen, who was president of the National Committee from March 1975 through 1987. David M. Lampton succeeded Rosen as president in 1988 and served until December 1997. His correspondence files are not found in the NCUSCR collection, but RG 9 does include copies of several of his talks, articles, and papers, as well as memos to the National Committee and congressional testimony, for the period 1987-2002.
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1975 (Box 36, Folder 348-350)
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1976 (Box 37, Folder 351-354)
    The file includes an annual calendar of the correspondence (placed at start of 1976 file).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1977 January - August (Box 37, Folder 355-356)
    The file includes an annual calendar of the correspondence (placed at the start of the 1977 files).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1977 September - December (Box 38, Folder 357)
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1978 (Box 38, Folder 358-361)
    The file includes an annual calendar of the correspondence (at the start of the 1978 files).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1979 January - March (Box 38, Folder 362)
    The file includes an annual calendar of the correspondence (placed at the start of the 1979 file).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1979 April - December (Box 39, Folder 363-366)
    For an annual calendar of the correspondence, see the start of the 1979 file (folder 362).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1980 January - June (Box 39, Folder 367-368)
    The file includes an annual calendar of the correspondence (placed at the start of the 1980 file).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1980 July - December (Box 40, Folder 369-370)
    For an annual calendar of the correspondence, see the start of the 1980 file (folder 367).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1981 (Box 40, Folder 371-375)
    The file includes an annual calendar of the correspondence (placed at the start of the 1981 file).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1982 (Box 41, Folder 376-380)
    The file includes an annual calendar of the correspondence (placed at the start of the 1982 file).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1983 January - August (Box 41, Folder 381-383)
    The file includes an annual calendar of the correspondence (placed at the start of the 1983 file).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1983 September - December (Box 42, Folder 384)
    For an annual calendar of the correspondence, see the start of the 1983 file (folder 381).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1984 (Box 42, Folder 385-389)
    The file includes an annual calendar of the correspondence (placed at the start of the 1984 file).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1985 January - June (Box 42, Folder 390-391)
    The file includes a calendar of the correspondence for 1985 - February 1986 (placed at the start of the 1985 file).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1985 July - 1986 February (Box 43, Folder 392-394)
    For a calendar of the correspondence, see the start of the 1985 file (folder 390).
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1986 March-September (Box 43, Folder 395-396)
    A calendar of the correspondence for March - September 1986 is found at the start of folder 395. Correspondence for January - September 1986 is numbered sequentially with the correspondence from 1985.
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1986 October - 1987 November (Box 43, Folder 397-399)
    A calendar of the correspondence for October 1986 - December 1987 is found at the start of folder 397. Beginning in July 1987, the files also include correspondence from president elect David M. Lampton.
  - Arthur H. Rosen Chronological Files, 1987 December - 1988 February (Box 43, Folder 400)
    David M. Lampton succeeded Rosen as president as of January 1988.
  - Arthur H. Rosen - Correspondence, 1974 - 1983 (Box 44, Folder 401-407)
    General correspondence, both incoming and outgoing. Includes personal notes, invitations, acknowledgements, exchange proposals, and employment and other inquiries.
  - Arthur H. Rosen - Correspondence, 1984 - 1987 (Box 45, Folder 408-410)
  - Arthur Rosen - Speaking Engagements, 1977-1981 (Box 45, Folder 411)
  - Arthur H. Rosen - Expense Statements, 1976-1977 (Box 45, Folder 412)
  - David M. Lampton - Memos and Articles (General), 1988-1995 (Box 45, Folder 413)
    Includes Down to Basics in the U. S. - China Relations, 1988; transcript of "America and the World," 1994 October 15; Memo of converstiaon with Acting Chinese Ambassador Zhou Wenzhong, 1995 August 29.
  - David M. Lampton - Toward a Vision of the National Committee, 1987 October 12 (Box 45, Folder 414)
    Draft, Toward a Vision of the National Committee as It Enters the 1990s.
  - David M. Lampton - Talk to American Chamber of Commerce, Hong Kong, 1988 September 9 (Box 45, Folder 415)
    Hong Kong Hilton.
  - David M. Lampton - Thinking about Managing a Complex Relationship among the U. S., China, and the Soviet Union, 1988 September (Box 45, Folder 416)
    Paper prepared for conference on "Economic Reform in China: Problems and Prospects," CATO Institute conference cosponsored with Fudan University, September 12-15, 1988, Shanghai Hilton International Hotel. Includes correspondence concerning conference and publication arrangements.
  - David M. Lampton - Talk to Miami University Conference on Trade with China, 1988 November 20 (Box 45, Folder 417)
    Oxford, OH.
  - David M. Lampton - Conferences and Talks (General), 1989 (Box 45, Folder 418)
    Speaking engagements, travel arrangements and expenses, program outlines.
  - David M. Lampton - Taiwan, Hong Kong, Beijing Trip, 1989 March (Box 45, Folder 419)
  - David M. Lampton - Bargaining, Interest, and Bureaucratic Politics in China, 1989 April 22 (Box 45, Folder 420)
    Paper entitled, "A Plum for a Peach." Prepared for conference on the Structure of Authority and Bureaucracy in China. Joint Committee on China of the ACLS and the SSRC, June 19-23, 1988, Tucson. File includes some correspondence concerning conference and publication planning.
  - David M. Lampton - China and U. S. - China Relations in the Wake of Tiananmen, 1989 September (Box 45, Folder 421)
    Draft report of "China in Flux" conference convened by the National Committee and the Johnson Foundation, July 7-9, 1989. Report published in National Committee China Policy Series, no. 2, September 1989.
  - David M. Lampton - Trip to China with Doak Barnett, 1989 September 9-23 (Box 45, Folder 422)
    Trip to China and Hong Kong.
  - David M. Lampton - Science applications International Corporation (SAIC) Workshop, 1989 September 26 (Box 45, Folder 423)
    Workshop on alternative futures for the People's Republic of China.
  - David M. Lampton - Los Angeles Rotary Club Speech, 1989 October 27 (Box 45, Folder 424)
  - David M. Lampton - Interview in South China Morning Post (A Sympathetic Ear), 1990 March 31 (Box 45, Folder 425)
  - David M. Lampton - Rebuild China - U. S. Relations (Christian Science Monitor Article), 1990 April 18 (Box 45, Folder 426)
    Co-authored with Raymond P. Shafer.
  - David M. Lampton - House Committee on Foreign Affairs Testimony, 1990 May 16 (Box 45, Folder 427)
    Testimony prepared for the Subcommittee on Human Rights and International Organizations, the Subcommittee on Asian and Pacific Affairs, and the Subcommittee on International Economic Policy and Trade.
  - David M. Lampton - Asia Trip (China, Hong Kong, Taiwan), 1990 September (Box 46, Folder 428)
  - David M. Lampton - China's Main Danger: Stagnation, Not Revolt (Christian Science Monitor Article), 1990 November 1 (Box 46, Folder 429)
  - David M. Lampton - China and Hong Kong Trip, 1991 May (Box 46, Folder 430)
    The original folder label gave the dates as May-June 1991.
  - David M. Lampton - Senate Finance Committee Testimony, 1991 June 19 (Box 46, Folder 431)
    Hearings on Extending China's M. F. N. (Most-Favored Nation) Status.
  - David M. Lampton - Senate Foreign Relations Committee Testimony, 1992 April 2 (Box 46, Folder 432)
    Hearings on Hong Kong's Reversion to China and Implications for U. S. Policy.
  - David M. Lampton - Hong Kong and the Rise of "Greater China": Policy Issues, 1992 June 16 (Box 46, Folder 433)
    Paper prepared for the Workshop on China in Transition: Implications for Hong Kong. Canada and Hong Kong Research Project, Joint Centre for Asia Pacific Studies, Toronto, June 11-12, 1992.
  - David M. Lampton - Press Coverage and Interviews (General), 1992 (Box 46, Folder 434)
  - David M. Lampton - Senate Energy and Natural Resources Committee Testimony, 1993 March 11 (Box 46, Folder 435)
    "United States and China Relations at a Crossroads." Hearing on the Energy Needs of the People's Republic of China." File includes shorter Oral Testimony and full paper.
  - David M. Lampton - Breaking Down China's Ruling Cliches (Asian Wall Street Journal Article), 1993 October 20 (Box 46, Folder 436)
  - David M. Lampton - The United States, China, and the MFN Decision: Doomsday Machine, Smart Bomb, or Blank?, 1993 November 16 (Box 46, Folder 437)
    Manuscript submission for James Lilley book on China and MFN status. Original version presented at Third Japan - U. S. Symposium on China, Japan Institute of International Affairs, Tokyo, July 15-16, 1993.
  - David M. Lampton - Challenges Facing the National Committee, circa 1993 (Box 46, Folder 438)
  - David M. Lampton - House National Security Committee Testimony, 1996 March 20 (Box 46, Folder 439)
    Chinese Security Objectives and U. S. Interests and Policy.
  - David M. Lampton - Managing U.S. - China Relations in the Twenty-First Century, 1999 (Box 46, Folder 440)
    Co-authored with Gregory C. May. Nixon Center report.
  - David M. Lampton - U.S. - China Relations in a Post - September 11th World, 2002 (Box 46, Folder 441)
    Co-authored with Richard Daniel Ewing. Nixon Center report.
  - John L. Holden - Mrs. Zhou Yongjun Request, 1999 (Box 46, Folder 442)
    Request for information on her husband, an activist who had been jailed in China.
- Clippings and Reference, 1948-2011; 15; 5.23 Cubic Feet 14 containers
  The Clippings and Reference series in RG 9 significantly documents two subject areas in particular, namely, U.S. Government Statements on China, 1948-1968; and the development and unfurling of events surrounding Beijing Spring, the Tiananmen Square uprising, the government crackdown, and its aftermath, 1989 and later.
  The U. S. Government Statements on China file consists of a typed compilation of statements and excerpts by U. S. leaders and officials, and several associated files of notes and clippings. The compilation appears to be a working manuscript, but it is not clear if it was ever published or otherwise distributed. Other files in this series concerning Public Opinion on China, 1966-1976, and official visitors and other Travelers to China, 1970s, provide a kind of complement to the government statements materials.
  Files on the Beijing Spring and Tiananmen contain clippings and contemporary press reports, eyewitness accounts, editorials, and other materials that document the events and consequences of the uprising and its repression and reactions to them.
  Finally, Series 15 also contains several files on relations between China and the U.S.S.R., as well as other general files on topics such as the Chinese economy, civil society, relations with Taiwan, etc.
  - China's Economy (General), 1986 (Box 15, Folder 155)
    Economic Relations in the Asian-Pacific Region (Brookings conference cosponsored with the Chinese Academy of Social Sciences, June 1985); Rong Yiren, On China's Economic Development and Open Policy (pamphlet).
  - China 1977 - 1979: Politics, Economy, Foreign Relations, and Trade (Box 15, Folder 156)
    New York Times Information Service, Issues and Trends.
  - China's Economy (Chase Manhattan Bank), 1980 (Box 15, Folder 157)
    Book prepared jointly by officials of the People's Republic of China and members of the technical staff of the Chase Manhattan Bank, N. A. The compilation appears to have been prepared for a China Economic Forum sponsored by Chase Manhattan Bank in May 1980.
  - China-United States Symposium on Financial Markets (Beijing), 1986 November 10-13 (Box 15, Folder 158)
    Sponsored by the People's Bank of China and the New York Stock Exchange. Summary of Major Addresses.
  - China-United States Symposium on Financial Markets (Beijing) - China Briefing Book, 1986 November 10-13 (Box 16, Folder 159)
    China Briefing Book for All Participants. Background materials provided by the NCUSCR and the U. S. Department of State.
  - Chinese Young Economists, Inc., Third Economics Symposium (Ann Arbor), 1987 June 12-13 (Box 16, Folder 160)
  - PRC- United States - U.S.S.R. (Relations), 1971-1986 (Box 29, Folder 273)
  - PRC - U.S.S.R. (Ideo-Cultural Relations), 1969-1986 (Box 29, Folder 274)
  - PRC - U.S.S.R. (Military Relations), 1973-1987 (Box 29, Folder 275)
  - PRC - U.S.S.R. (Political Relations), 1969-1986 (Box 29, Folder 276-277)
  - PRC - U.S.S.R. (Press Releases), 1973-1979 (Box 29, Folder 278-279)
  - PRC - United Nations (Relations), 1976-1982 (Box 30, Folder 280-281)
    Clippings and press releases.
  - U. S. Government Statements on China, 1948-1966 (Box 30, Folder 282)
    Typed compilation of statements on China by U. S. political and military leaders and officials.
  - U. S. Government Statements on China - Notes, 1948-1961 (Box 30, Folder 283-284)
    Excerpts from statements on China, arranged in chronological file of notes. The file was presumably compiled by NCUSCR program assistant Patti Hagan.
  - U. S. Statements on China - Notes, 1962-1968 May (Box 30, Folder 285-286)
    Typed excerpts and clippings, arranged in chronological file. Materials for 1967-1968 are mainly clippings. Subjects include Communist China and U. S. foreign policy in Asia.
  - Recent Statements on U. S. - China Relations, 1967-1968 (Box 30, Folder 287)
    Typed compilations of statements by U. S. government officials and international sources.
  - U. S. Statements on China Trade, 1964-1968 (Box 30, Folder 288)
    Typed compilations of statements by political and business leaders and organizations.
  - U. S. Statements on China (Source Articles) (Working File), 1963-1968 (Box 31, Folder 289-290)
    Speeches, clippings, and correspondence. Original file labeled "Patti" (Patti Hagan).
  - Statements on U. S. - China Relations (Source Articles), 1968 April - August (Box 31, Folder 291)
    Copies of speeches, press releases, and clippings included in the Recent Statements compilation.
  - U. S. Statements on China (Source Articles), 1966-1969 (Box 31, Folder 292)
    Original folders noted that these statements were not yet recorded or included in the general compilation list.
  - U.S. Statements on China (Source Articles), 1967 (Box 31, Folder 293)
    Original folder labeled "1967 Ready."
  - U.S. Statements on China (Source Articles), 1968 (Box 31, Folder 294)
  - U.S. Statements on China, Vietnam, and Southeast Asia (Source Articles), 1965-1968 (Box 31, Folder 295)
  - U. S. Statements on China (Draft), 1948-1950; 1952-1959 (Box 32, Folder 296-298)
    Draft compilation of statements and quotes on China, cut and pasted and arranged chronologically, with identifying labels.
  - U. S. - China Relations concerning Vietnam and Cambodia, 1972-1976 (Box 32, Folder 299)
  - Statements on China by U. S. Government Officials, 1970-1971; 1975-1976 (Box 32, Folder 300-301)
  - Public Opinion on China - General, 1971-1976 (Box 32, Folder 302)
    U. S. public opinion on China.
  - Public Opinion - Editorials and Media Coverage of China, 1970-1976 (Box 32, Folder 303)
  - Public Opinion on China - U. S. Political Leaders, 1971-1975 (Box 33, Folder 304)
  - Public Opinion on China - Lobbies, 1971-1976 (Box 33, Folder 305)
  - Public Opinion on China - Polls, 1966-1976 (Box 33, Folder 306)
  - Public Opinion - Gallop Poll on China, 1971 (Box 33, Folder 307)
    The National Committee prepared questions on China for use in a Gallop Poll. File contains correspondence and copies of questionnaires.
  - U.S. - China Relations - Historic Background, 1967-1975; Still Images: 2 black and white 5x7 glossy prints. (Box 33, Folder 308)